Guide to the International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen, Local 1 Records and Photographs WAG.118
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen, Local 1 Records and Photographs
circa 1880-1990, undated
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen. Local 1 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Lanzafame, Santo
WAG.118
48 Linear Feet in 47 record cartons and 1 oversize flat box.
The International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen, Local 1 was granted a charter by the National Union of Bricklayers of the U.S.A. on October 17, 1868 in Brooklyn, New York and is one of the oldest continuously-existing locals in New York City. The National Union of Bricklayers was one of the first unions to support the eight-hour work day. The collection consists of early ledgers of Locals 1 and 9, as well as correspondence, ephemera, photographs, scrapbooks and audio tapes of Local 1 and other locals it merged with, including Locals 9, 21, 34, 41 and 66. Materials date from the 1880s to the 1990s.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of records of International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen, Local 1 of Brooklyn, New York and other locals it merged with, including Local 9 of Brooklyn, Local 41 of Woodside, Queens, and locals 21, 30, 31, 34, 37, 66 and 84. Materials and documents date from the 1880s to the 1990s and include ledger books, minutes, contracts, correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, ephemera and audiotapes. Early ledgers of Locals 1 and 9 date from the 1880s to the 1930s and include minutes, dues records, expense and benefits books and apprentice lists. Photographs include portraits of individual members, union events, and group portraits of union members from the 1920s to the 1980s. A 1940s-era scrapbook from Local 41 includes head shots and group portraits of union members and related clippings. A photographs album that appears to date from the 1920s-1930s includes approximately 105 small black and white head shots of union members with names written in pencil under each.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen, Local 1, in 1998. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1998.020 and 1998.021.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragility of materials in Boxes 1 and 2, researchers must use the microfilm of the early minutes of Local 9 (microfilm collection number R7459). Also because of fragility, advance notice is required before using a 1920s-1930s-era photographs album in Box 48.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The National Union of Bricklayers of the U.S.A. was organized on October 16, 1865 and granted a charter to Local No. 1 in Brooklyn, New York, on October 17, 1868, making Local 1 one of the oldest continuously-existing locals in New York City. The National Union of Bricklayers was one of the first unions to support the eight-hour work day, a priority for delegates from its New York locals to its 1869 Convention. In 1881, the National Union of Bricklayers became an international union. A reorganized charter was granted in 1910 when the International became Bricklayers, Masons, and Plasterers International Union of America. In 1916, the union became affiliated with the American Federation of Labor. From its beginnings the union emphasized apprenticeship training, wages, working conditions, and benefits for union members and their families.
The union's records illustrate the early dominance of Irish American and Irish immigrant members in the union -- many of them sons of bricklayers. In the 1930s and 1940s members from Irish and Italian ethnic backgrounds clashed, as Irish membership dwindled, and Italian members brought in more family members. By the mid-1980s, union operations were run at the district and international level, rather than at the local level, and local politics and power became less important. In 1986, Local 1 had 447 members, half of whom were African American and Latino, and the remainder were mostly of Italian origin. During the 1980s and 1990s, the International operated a federally-funded program called the Job Corps for Disadvantaged Youth, which trained female as well as male apprentices for Local 1.
Since its founding, Local 1 merged with several other locals, including locals 9, 21, 30, 31, 34, 37, 41, 66 and 84. Local 1's members have worked on New York City landmarks such as Grand Central Station, the Chrysler Building, the Metropolitan Life Building, the American Museum of Natural History, Lincoln Center, the Cloisters, the Frick Museum, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and thousands of office and residential buildings.
Sources:
Bates, Harry. Bricklayers' Century of Craftsmanship: A History of the Bricklayers, Masons and Plasterers' International Union of America. Washington, D.C.: Bricklayers, Masons and Plasterers' International Union of America Washington, D.C., 1955.
Hommel, Claudia. New York City Labor Records Survey, Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, 1986.
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scrapbooks.; Ledgers (account books).; Building trades -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States.; Bricklayers |x Labor unions.; Labor unions -- New York (State); Photographs.; International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen. Local 1 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Lanzafame, Santo
- Local 9: Ledgers and Minutes, undated (Box 1)
- Local 9: Ledgers and Minutes, undated (Box 2)
- Local 9: Ledgers and Minutes, undated (Box 3)
- Local 9: Address Books, 1934-1940 (Box 4)
- Local 9: PR Files, 1963 (Box 4)
- Local 9: Minutes, undated (Box 4)
- Local 9: Old Contracts, undated (Box 4)
- Local 41: Correspondence, 1980s (Box 5)
- Local 41: Correspondence, 1950s-1970s (Box 6)
- Local 41: Contracts, 1950s-1970s (Box 6)
- Photographs, undated (Box 7)
- Frank Alessi: Correspondence, 1989 (Box 7)
- Photograph Plates, undated (Box 7)
- Local 9: Ledger and Minutes, 1909-1938 (Box 8)
- Local 9: Ledger Book and Minutes, 1921-1924 (Box 9)
- Local 21: Correspondence (Box 10)
- Local 66: Correspondence, undated (Box 10)
- Local 66: Journeyman Applications, undated (Box 10)
- Local 34: Correspondence, 1980s (Box 11)
- Local 34, 1980s (Box 12)
- Local 34: Correspondence, undated (Box 13)
- Deceased and Dropped Members, undated (Box 13)
- Deceased and Dropped Members, undated (Box 14)
- Local 34: General Correspondence, 1985 (Box 14)
- Local 34: Correspondence, 1990s (Box 15)
- Local 34: Correspondence, 1991 (Box 16)
- Group Photographs, 1910 (Box 16)
- Kmmiti Job Information, undated (Box 16)
- Election Results, 1910 (Box 16)
- Locals 30 and 41: Legal Decisions, 1910 (Box 16)
- Local 34: Correspondence, 1986 (Box 17)
- Local 34: Correspondence, 1987 (Box 18)
- Local 34: Correspondence, 1988 (Box 19)
- Local 34: Correspondence, 1989 (Box 19)
- Local 34: Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 20)
- Local 34: Correspondence, 1990 (Box 21)
- Local 66: Correspondence, undated (Box 21)
- Local 66: Tapes of Board Meetings, 1990-1991 (Box 21)
- Trade Agreements and Constitutions, 1947-1967, undated (Box 21)
- Local 66: Correspondence, 1990s (Box 22)
- Local 66: Dues Receipts, circa 1980s (Box 22)
- Local 66: Correspondence, 1990s (Box 23)
- Dropped and Deceased Members Book, undated (Box 23)
- Dues Book, undated (Box 23)
- Local 1: Photographs of Life Members, 1947 (Box 23)
- Local 30: Correspondence, circa 1970-1990 (Box 24)
- Local 66: Correspondence, undated (Box 25)
- New York District Committee, undated (Box 25)
- Legal Dues, undated (Box 25)
- Local 34: Minutes, 1900-1942 (Box 26)
- District Committee Reports, undated (Box 26)
- Local 34: Minutes, undated (Box 27)
- Local 66: Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 28)
- Local 34: Minutes, 1953-1957, 1964-1968 (Box 28)
- Local 66: Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 29)
- Tapes of Executive Committee Meetings, 1988-1990, undated (Box 30)
- Local 1: Correspondence, undated (Box 30)
- Local 66: Correspondence, undated (Box 30)
- Local 66: Correspondence, undated (Box 31)
- Ledger Books, 1960s (Box 32)
- Old Minutes, 1911, 1940s-1950s (Box 32)
- Correspondence, undated (Box 32)
- Local 9: Old Election Ballots, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 32)
- Local 9: Membership Lists, 1960s (Box 32)
- Local 9: Minutes, undated (Box 32)
- Local 9: Ledger Books, undated (Box 33)
- Local 9: Correspondence, undated (Box 33)
- Local 66: Correspondence, undated (Box 33)
- Local 66: Correspondence, undated (Box 34)
- Local 21: Correspondence, undated (Box 34)
- Local 9: Ledgers and Minutes, 1930s (Box 35)
- Local 9: Ledgers and Minutes, 1930s (Box 36, Box 49)
- Local 9: Ledgers and Minutes, 1880s (Box 37)
- Initiations, undated (Box 38)
- Transfers, 1920s (Box 38)
- Local 34: Photographs, undated (Box 39)
- Local 34: Correspondence, undated (Box 39)
- Local 66: General Files, undated (Box 40)
- New York State Conference, undated (Box 40)
- Local 66: Contracts, undated (Box 40)
- Local 66: Organization Tapes, undated (Box 40)
- Local 66: Minutes, 1980s (Box 40)
- Minutes, 1980s (Box 41)
- Book - History, undated (Box 41)
- Local 9: Ledgers, circa 1895-circa 1932 (Box 42)
- Local 9: Ledgers, Member Address Book, Candidates Book, 1910-1927 (Box 43)
- Local 9: Items Removed from Minutes, 1885-1936, 1963-1973 (Box 44)
- Local 1: Welfare Fund Ledger; Local 3: Dues Books; Printed Materials from Building Trades; Worker Safety Legislation Proposals; Local 41: General Correspondence, 1885-1909, 1983-1990 (Box 45)
- Local 1: Ledger; Local 9: Minutes, 1896, 1929-1930 (Box 46)
- Local 9: Ledgers and Membership Lists, 1906-1930, 1957-1979 (Box 47)
- Local 1: Apprenticeship Training Photographs, circa 1995-circa 1997 (Box 48)
- Local 1: Photographs of Restoration of Building at 71st and Park, circa 1990 (Box 48)
- Local 41: Scrapbook [Includes Clippings and Photographs of Members], circa 1940s (Box 48)
- Scrapbook [Includes 105 black and white photographs; names written in pencil under each], circa 1920s-circa 1930s (Box 48)
- Photographs of Union Officers and Events [Includes Group and Individual Portraits], circa 1930s-circa 1980s (Box 48)
- Head shots of Union Members, circa 1920s-circa 1930s (Box 48)
- Memorial Poster for Thomas F. Murphy, circa 1989 (Box 48)
- Local 1: Photograph of 90th Anniversary, Nov 20, 1964 (Box 48)
- Archived Website, Dec 5, 2012-ongoing
  Scope and Content Note
  The International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen, Local 1 was granted a charter by the National Union of Bricklayers of the U.S.A. on October 17, 1868 in Brooklyn, New York and is one of the oldest continuously-existing locals in New York City. The union represents bricklayers, plasterers, stonesetters, and pointers, cleaners and caulkers. The website contains their newsletter, events, and news listings.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.